# Vihag Guru

# Professional Summary

She is a highly skilled professional with 14 years of experience in **regional planning**, **project management**, **and stakeholder coordination**. She has a strong background in rural development, urban planning, and infrastructure projects. She has made significant contributions to initiatives such as the **Shyama Prasad Mukherji Rurban Mission and Smart City projects**. She possesses excellent project management skills and is proficient in **various software tools**, **including GIS and remote sensing**. Her expertise and experience in **program management and policy formulation have resulted in successful project implementations**. She is a dedicated and goal-oriented professional, committed to driving sustainable development.

## **Experience**

## REGIONAL PLANNING SPECIALIST 02/2019 - 03/2023

NIRD&PR under Ministry of Rural Development

Formulation of policies and long-term strategies related to macro planning of rural areas. Spatial plan prepared for Shamlaji Cluster in Gujarat, Singarayakonda cluster Andhra Pradesh, Nirbhoypur in Tripura. Prepared Economic Plan templates to boost rural livelihood through Agri Services & Processing, Skill development linked to economic activities in 300 Rurban Growth Centres. Identified cluster development activities for Aibawk cluster of Mizoram and monitored the project completion. Conducted policy research, including in-depth study of Panchayati Raj Act, Town & Country Act for Pan India. Guidelines preparation for rural planning and reforms. Project analysis for economic development of rurban clusters in North East. Prepared Rural area plan preparation manual, and Service level benchmarking for preparation of regional plans. Engaged in qualitative and quantitative research to develop GIS module platforms for planning, monitoring, and evaluation of Rurban Clusters. Prepared annual action plans and quarter plans, assisted in financial budgeting of the Mission. Coordinated with stakeholders, central ministries, and state/UTs for program implementation. Conducted capacity building activities, prepared Memorandum of Understandings (MoUs) with research/mentor institutes and government bodies. Involved in impact studies, social audits, and development of Learning Management System for capacity building stakeholders in collaboration of BISAG -N. Conducted workshops, conferences for State officials on a bi-annual basis for approximately 250 participants via online and off-line formats. Analyzed and provided inputs for various Cabinet Notes, SFC/EFC Notes, and other issues received from Central Ministries.

**VP & AVP** 06/2015 - 12/2018 **YES Bank Limited** 

Project Management for Smart City of Dharamshala and Ranchi. Empanelment of YES BANK in Ministry of Housing and Urban Affairs for Municipal Bond Advisory. Urban, Rural, and Health Sector reviews and action plan analysis. Portfolio management for municipal bodies and Pan India Team Management under Government Banking for portfolio penetration in urban, rural, health and education.

**ASSISTANT MANAGER** 04/2011 - 06/2015

Infrastructure Development Corporation Limited, IIDC

**Project Management Consultant** to Delhi Mumbai Industrial Corridor (DMIC) Project under National Industrial Corridor Development Corporation.

Monitoring, supervision, quantitative and qualitative research, technical support, bid process management, and stakeholder management, coordination with state and central ministries for implementation of DMIC

projects like Shendra Bidkin Industrial Area near Aurangabad Maharashtra (Phase 1:18.55 sq.kms), Dholera Special Investment Region, Gujarat (Phase 1: 22.5sq.kms) & Integrated Industrial Township - Greater Noida, Uttar Pradesh (3sq.kms).

Suggested project-specific institutional structures for Public-Private Partnerships.

#### **SENIOR OFFICER 12/2008 - 03/2011**

Infrastructure Development Corporation Limited, IIDC

Prepared a report on the Development of the Southern Economic Corridor in East Asia between Myanmar to Vietnam via Cambodia. Conducted demographic, social, and natural resources studies of corridor countries. Identified industrial and infrastructural gaps and suggested measures to promote industrial and infrastructure development Khushkhera - Bhiwadi Neemrana Investment zone having an area of 200Sq.Kms under Delhi Mumbai industrial corridor project. Provided advisory assistance for the commercial development of surplus railway land to Rail Land Development Authority. Involved in conceptual planning, market demand assessment, project structuring, bidding strategy, and evaluation and selection of bidders for Railway Land including Railway Colony at Sarai Rohilla and Ashok Vihar in North Delhi. Provided technical support for appraising, supervising, and monitoring projects. Managed bid processes, stakeholder management, project coordination with state departments, environmental clearance, land acquisition, and feasibility studies of Khushkhera - Bhiwadi Neemrana Investment zone (200 sq.kms) and Jodhpur - Pali - Marwar industrial area (150sq.kms).

## MANAGEMENT TRAINEE 06/2008 - 12/2008 Infrastructure Development Corporation Limited,, Ranchi

Concept note on Haj Complex, Jail Complex
Pre feasibility study for Air cargo hub in Jharkhand

# Core Qualifications

- Ms Word, Ms PowerPoint, Ms Project, Ms Excel, Ms Outlook
- · GIS, Remote Sensing
- Adobe Illustrator, Adobe Photoshop, iMovie & Canva

## Education

Master of Technology, Urban & Regional Planning, 2008 CEPT University, Ahmedabad, Gujarat

Master, Arts (Geography), 2006 Delhi School of Economics, New Delhi

### Certifications

Diploma in Management from ICFAI University, Tripura Certificate in Business Basics from ICFAI University, Tripura

Attended training programs on Japanese Project Management for Infrastructure Development in India (AOTS, Japan)